so a person asks um
says they say I've often been thinking
about the way the Buddha talks
about people who like a sense of urgency
as being Intoxicated by Youth Life or
health and I was wondering if you could explain
and I was wondering if you could explain
in what way being younger healthy is the
same as being Intoxicated by alcohol for
instance and what do those things have in common
and what do those things have in common
so why is it called an intoxication yeah so the main
the main
principle about being intoxicated
whether it's with alcohol with drugs or
with anything is that
is that
you have to
be forgetting the dangers that come with
intoxication in order to be intoxicated with it
in order to be intoxicated with it
in other words you can't really be
deliberately knowingly intoxicating
yourself with
alcohol for example
being fully aware of it and deliberately
fully aware of it and deliberately
making yourself intoxicated with it you
have to forget about
um or ignore
all of the other things that come when
you engage with alcohol the the
carelessness that it might lead you into
the fact that you will have symptoms
later on the fact that you might have an
accident because of whatever
and
and you just kind of have to go with
this and not see any danger in it
later on
and what makes this similar to
intoxication the reason why then these
things are described as intoxications
intoxication of Youth or of Health for
example
what it really has uh has in common is
that
while things feel okay as in while
you're enjoying the the things that come
with being young with being healthy
with being alive
you forget
or you ignore not that you forget you
you ignore because you you do know these
things you ignore the the underside of
that or the other side of that that's
always inescapable so you know when when you're
inescapable so you know when when you're
healthy
it's an inescapable fact that you are
liable to get sick
when you're young just even the word
young already implies old age on the
other hand under it otherwise you
wouldn't you wouldn't be able to even
think of Youth it wouldn't make any
sense as an even an idea
the word life
has death as its counterpart
so
the reason then that these things are
described as intoxications is that
you when you're when you're intoxicated
with youth when you're intoxicated with
health and we're intoxicated with life
you're not seeing that other side that
is there and because of not seeing that
other side that is there similarly as
with being intoxicated though with
alcohol you you become careless and you
do things that
um then
that then kind of increase the
engagement with that which is subject to
youth to life and to
um and to health and is also then
equally subject to old age sickness and
death and because of that you are prey
to that other side of those things so
like if a person were not to engage with
alcohol it would be impossible for them
to have a hangover it would be
impossible for them to like you know go
into debt debt because of becoming an
alcoholic or whatever
would be impossible for them to suffer
liver circles on account of alcohol now
you can't help like having a body that
is
um that is subject to old age sickness
and death
but what you can help is being
intoxicated with that body and therefore
um
it delighting in is
um you know following its wants its
desires wherever they lead you
um being a slave to it
and when you keep being on a slave to it
it's gonna kill you at the end it's
gonna it's it's gonna torture you it's
gonna start it's gonna start making you
suffer the other thing that has in common being
the other thing that has in common being
an intoxication is this like it it
basically follows this principle of
you know when people when people are are
intoxicated with again let's say alcohol
it's not that they
then are completely unaware and or don't
are completely unaware and or don't
experience any and bad things that come
on account of alcohol like they're quite
bothered by those things
but the thing is that they don't see the
connection between the two while they're
engaging with this and otherwise they
wouldn't engage with it and that's
exactly again what makes it an
intoxication that's
it's it's not something you're going to
do deliberately
you're losing perspective naturally
that's that's always the common
principle of any intoxication losing
perspective on account of it
and so in this in again the same way
you know because you can't even suffer
sickness but suffering sickness doesn't
make you lose the intoxication
because you only feel the bother of us
while you're sick
and you don't see the connection that
that bother of feeling sick while you're
bothered me by being sick has to just
you know forgetting about about it and
be and being intoxicated with all the
things that you can only get on account
of being healthy like good food for
example you know you can you take for
granted that it always takes good tastes
good when every whenever you're
um when whatever food you might like or
have desire for
when you're sick with particular type of
illness that same food has no appeal
whatsoever and you just take for granted
all the time completely that
um that this that this food always
tastes good and you don't realize that
just the fact that that food is
enjoyable to you depends on the fact
that your body happens to be healthy
right now
so
and yeah and then again when you become
sick you'll be bothered by it at the
time but because of because of that
but because of because of that
intoxication of Health
you will be able to completely forget
once the thickness goes away and food
tastes good again
you won't you won't see the danger of
the lighting in that food
so I'd say it kind of boils down to that
basically so you in in order to
um not suffer the Perils of old age of
sickness and death you need to start
seeing them as the counterpart of what
you're engaging with right now of the
pleasures that you can have on account
of this young healthy alive body while
you're young while you're young healthy
and alive and not waiting for sickness
to hit you for old age to come to you
certainly not for death
and you need to also start stop seeing
it's like you need to stop seeing these
things like death for example people
always think of it as like life is first
and there's just a little death on the
end like you know oh sure all life ends
in death it would be better to say all
death has to begin with life
you know death is kind of you can you
can basically say those two things in
either direction
so if you start seeing life as the
necessary counterpart of death you
realize that actually death is is what
you have
as the
as the underneath or the other side of
the underbelly of everything that you're
experiencing